Okay, so today
we're going to take
a look at a very
common problem.
I would bet that lower
back pain is the single
biggest contributor to the
opioid epidemic, and if it's
not the biggest, it's
certainly in the top three.
Most people will get this
at some point in their
lives, and it usually
resolves spontaneously, but it
also usually comes back,
and that's typically because
people don't address the
underlying pathomechanics.
Even if you don't go
into a musculoskeletal
-related specialty, and
you end up doing some
kind of primary care,
you will deal with this
a lot. So it behooves
you to understand it.
The statistic on the bottom
is interesting. People
kind of throw this around
a lot. I think it has
more to do with how
chronic pain becomes a
nervous system disorder rather
than a persisting lumbar
issue per se. But because
low back pain is so
common, I think it just
gets conflated with it.
So the lumbar vertebrae
from the side.
Two things to notice here.
The spinous process and
inferior articular process
are below the level of the
body. The inferior process
projects anterior lateral,
and you can see that well
here, as well as here.
What you can't see so well
is the superior articular
process and how it
projects medially and
posteriorly, but from the
top view it's pretty clear.
So the superior facets
line up with the
inferior facets to form
these articulations.
An AP view of the normal spine.
Spinous processes are
in a straight line and
at the midpoint of the
vertebral body, so not
to the right or to
the left, which would
indicate that the vertebrae
is rotated somehow.
Here we zoom in on
one segment, L2, L3.
And here I outline the
structures that you should be
able to identify. The
spinous process is on the
lower half of the body or
just jutting right below it.
An x-ray is two
dimensional. So you're
seeing the lateral
facing component of the
inferior articular
process and the medial
facing component of
the superior process.
The arrow is on the
inferior vertebral notch.
And when you stack
the vertebrae, the
notches make up the
intervertebral foramen,
which is where the
spinal nerve exits.
When you stack the vertebrae,
you also get the space
between the bodies. And you
can't see a disc on x-ray,
so the space becomes this
sort of proxy for it. You
want to see good, normal
space between the vertebrae,
and that's an indication
that the the disc is healthy.
Now an x-ray beam is kind
of like your line of sight.
If you squat down and
look at your kitchen table
dead on you're just going
to see the edge of it.
But if you stand up and
look down at it you see the
edge and the table surface.
Here the x-ray beam
is lined up with L1 and
L2 and the vertebral end
plates are crisp there. I
outlined it in light blue.
When you're looking
down at L4-L5, you're
seeing through them,
and the surface of
it overlaps, and it
makes the space look
more narrow than it actually
is, if that makes sense.
Same thing with foramen.
I outlined it in orange,
and at the top, it looks
really, really wide
because the lamina are
lined up perfectly,
but when you're looking
down at L4-L5, the lamina
are kind of staggered,
and so one of them is
sort of encroaching on
what is normal space.
An oblique view of
the lumbar spine.
People think this looks
like a Scotty dog.
The pedicle is supposed to
be the eye. The transverse
process is the snout. The
superior articular process
is the ear. The inferior
articular process is
the front leg. The light
green is the neck. That's the
pars inter articularis.
And the lamina is, I guess,
supposed to be the body,
which is the dark green.
I guess I kind of see it.
Okay, so now some pathology.
Discs obviously can cause pain.
It's usually in
younger and middle-aged
adults. A bulge is where
the whole disc moves
outside of the margin
of the vertebral body.
A herniation is where
there's tears in the
fibers of the annulus
fibrosus, and the
pulposis extravasates
through those tears.
It has inflammatory mediators,
so when it gets to the
edge of the annulus, because
it's innervated, it's
going to cause pain. The
pain is felt over the back
itself, which we refer to
as axial, but it can also
refer pain to the back of
the thigh or even the leg.
If the disc either pushes
on a nerve root or if the
pulposus contacts the nerve
root and causes inflammation,
that can cause radicular
pain in the thigh or
the leg. If that isn't referred
pain, don't get confused.
That's actual neurological
pain in the leg. So
it can be difficult to tease
one out from the other.
The direction of the
arrow is how a radial
tear will propagate,
usually it starts
in the center and it
makes its way out.
The bulge, the
tear, the herniation
can happen in any
number of directions.
Straight back is
a central bulge or
herniation and if
it's big it can
compress the spine
or the cauda equina.
At 1 and 11 o'clock the disc
extends to the sub
articular recess.
This would most likely get
the traversing nerve root.
So let's say we're looking
down at L4 from the
top. So this would be
the L3-L4 disc that we're
considering. Here the disc
would affect the L4 nerve root
as it passes through. The
L3 root is lateral and
it's already exiting at
this point. Now if you look
at the 2 and 10 o'clock
positions, there it would be
hitting the L3 nerve root
and that we call a foraminal
disc bulge or foraminal
disc herniation. There's
other possibilities but
these are the main ones.
Sitting puts more pressure
on your disc than any
other position. The more
you do it, the worse it is.
Obesity shifts your
center of gravity forward.
So your paraspinal muscles
have to compensate. It's
kind of like your trunk
wants to fall forward
and so your paraspinal
muscles need to hold you up.
Those muscles, if you
look at it, they run
parallel to the spine.
So as the origin and
insertion move closer
So together, they're
going to generate a
compression on your disc.
Same thing with heavy
lifting. You're engaging all
these core muscles to stabilize
yourself when you pick
something up, and the
paraspinal muscles too. And
both obesity and with heavy
lifting, you're also kind
of carrying this extra weight
that's also compressing
on the spine in addition
to the muscle compression.
Some patients feel like they
did one particular thing
and it hurt them. but in
reality most people have
kind of been abusing these
discs for years but because
most of the disc is
insensate they won't really
feel it until it gets sort
of to that critical end
that periphery of the annulus
bending forward if you
can see it kind of brings
the vertebral end plates
closer together and it mashes
down on this now inflamed
disc so that's going to
irritate your symptoms.
Bending back on the
flip side opens that
space up and gives it
some breathing room.
I always rule out leg
weakness because if it's not
addressed, it can get permanent.
That can happen from a
disc that's compressing
the spine or the nerve root
badly enough. I always
check for bowel or bladder
dysfunction or numbness in the
upper medial thighs. That's
S2 to S4 weakness from
compression of the cauda
equina. That is an emergency.
If you think this is even
remotely possible you get
an mri immediately posture
can give you some clues
some patients have a side
shift to their trunk which
essentially takes the
pressure off of the disc if
there's any foot slapping
or toe dropping this is
happening during gait that
can be a problem when
you heel strike the floor
pushes up on your calcaneus
and the foot seesaws at the
ankle it makes your main
part of your foot want
to slam down your tibialis
anterior eccentrically
contracts to ease your foot
down but if it's weak from
an l4 root lesion the
foot will slap down hard
dorsi flexing your foot
happens when you're swinging
your leg through so that
your toes don't catch on
the ground if they catch you
can sort of trip and fall
so these are the kind of
common things that most
physicians recognize as
weakness from your lumbar
spine because l4 is one of
the more common lesions.
Strengths, sensation,
reflexes, these
are all things that
you should know.
Here you have hip flexion
at L2, knee extension
at L3, dorsiflexion at L4,
L5 is specific for extensor
hallucis longus, and
plantar flexion for S1.
A straight rag glaze goes
like this. you lift the
leg with the knee straight
if they get pain you don't
know if it's muscle pain
or if it's coming from the
spine so at the point
that they get pain say 30
degrees of hip flexion you
bring it down just a little
to where they have no pain
again then you dorsiflex
the foot if the pain comes
back it's a good indication
that it's coming from
the spine because in
dorsiflexing the foot you're
putting tension through all
the connective tissue up
the leg at the nerve root
if you let go of their foot
and the pain goes away you
can have them flex their
head and neck and if the
pain comes back that's a
really good indication because
now you're putting tension
back into that system but
from the other end and so
flexing your head and neck
and making pain go down your
leg is a very very strong
indication that it's coming
from their nerve root
So the Kirkcaldy-Willis
cascade goes something
like this. You have a disc
herniation that leads to
a loss of disc height
because you've lost some
volume in the disc. Now
the vertebrae rest closer
together. So when you
move, the vertebral bodies
are connecting more and
that causes inflammation.
On MRI, those are
called modic changes.
The facet joints are
more compressed too, so
the cartilage starts
to wear down quicker.
Arthritis in the facet
joints will cause back pain,
and those joints can also
refer pain to the legs,
just like the disc did.
But when you have an
arthritic joint, a common
reaction is to form bony
bridging osteophytes to stop
the movement in a painful
joint. But that extra
bone can crowd out the
nerve root in the foramen
and the spinal cord in
the central canal. So
like an injured disc, the
degenerative changes can
cause back pain, referred
pain to the legs, and they
can lead to nerve root
compression and therefore
true neurogenic leg pain.
They can also lead to
central canal stenosis
where you have both
legs affected and spinal
cord compression happens
much more commonly with
degenerative changes
than it does with a
central disc displacement.
And you can have all
these changes that cause
no back pain at all,
but only stenosis and only
neurogenic leg issues.
So again, the presentation
is very, very variable.
Now because this is
degenerative, it does sort
of become gradual and
progressive over time.
Claudecation usually
means leg pain with
activity because of
poor circulation.
So you have vascular
compromise and muscles will
hurt because they're not
getting the oxygen they
need, especially when they're
working, like walking.
Neurogenic claudecation
mimics that because they get
leg pain with walking.
It's not happening because
of poor blood flow though.
when you walk, your lumbar
spine goes through these
repetitive cycles of
extension. Extension with
an already narrow foramen
is enough to bring on symptoms,
and it usually happens
at a predictable distance
before the pain sets
in. When they sit down, the
lumbar spine flexes, the
intervertebral foramen
opens up, and the pain goes
away. And this really does
mimic vascular claudication
because sitting down also
means that the muscle
is taking a break from
activity, and it's giving the
circulation and opportunity
catch up with it. So
you really have to tease
things out carefully here.
One thing that's classic
for neurogenic claudication
is the shopping cart
sign. So they lean
forward on a cart or on
their walker when they're
walking around. It's kind
of like sitting in that
it flexes the lumbar
spine and it opens up the
neural foramen. So it gives
this nerve root space.
The chem test is essentially
spinal extension with
side bending to the affected
side. If they get symptoms
like this just standing
in that position, that's a
pretty good indication that
it's coming from the spine.
So here is your normal spine.
Here is the degenerated
spine in an AP view.
I want you to look
around those facet joints
and look at how much
more cloudy they are.
There's all this sclerosis
and bony deposition.
Look at the decreased
spaces between
the bodies is very different.
The normal on the left
and the degenerated
on the right. Look at
those osteophytes on
the anterior body.
The radio-dense facets
compared to the normal.
The narrow disc spaces.
Bondylo-listhesis means
one vertebrae is slipping
forward over another.
If the edge of the top
vertebrae is in the middle
of the width of the bottom
vertebrae, that's a grade
2. If the back edge of
the top vertebrae is over
the front edge of the
one below it, so they're
not overlapping at all
anymore, that's a grade 4.
I've never seen that one.
The most common is degenerative.
The disc loses volume,
so essentially it's like
a half deflated balloon,
so it moves around more.
The osteophytes also disrupt
the normal surfaces, so it
sits kind of off kilter.
But if it's 2 millimeters
off, let's say, which
would be a grade one.
And then you shoot x-rays
with a spine inflection
and then again an extension
and it's still just
two millimeters in all
those different positions.
That's a statical asthesis.
It's not a big deal. I
do nothing with that.
Now, ismic happens
because of a fracture.
In the spine, the fracture
is going to be, in
this case, in the pars
inter articularis.
And that fracture is
called the spondylolysis.
This happens mostly in
young athletes, and I
mean like high school.
So, if you have someone
that young with back
pain, you get an x-ray.
The one on the left
with the arrowheads
shows the pars
inter articularis.
The full arrow shows the
pars with a fracture.
On the right, you can
clearly see the step-off. By
convention, the line is
usually looked at in the
posterior bodies, and it's
usually traced so that
you can see here L4 is
about 25% offset from L5.
and so this would
be a grade one.
Here I'm just reminding
you of that Scotty dog and
the break happens at the
neck of the Scotty dog.
Okay let's get away from
pathology for a minute
and talk about some
diagnostic modalities.
MRI can be quite useless
in patients with back
pain. First of all please
understand that unless a
test is going to change
your treatment plan
there's little point in
getting it. Second of all
there's a lot of false
positives. The numbers depend
on the particular study
you look at, but roughly
40-ish percent of
asymptomatic people across
the board have at least one
level of disc degeneration,
bulge, herniation,
arthropathy, whatever.
These are people
with no symptoms
at all. So when
will I get an MRI?
I always got them before
doing spine injections
because I don't want
to stick a needle
in there without
knowing what's going on.
If I'm worried about
an infection after a
procedure, I'll get
one. If there's leg
issues in general that
don't get better with
therapy and manipulation,
I'll get one.
If there's any leg
weakness, true weakness at
all, I'll definitely get
it. And if there's any
bowel or bladder issues,
I'll get it immediately.
And while it is primarily
a soft tissue modality, you
can get a pretty good read
on bone too. So if there's
some concern about metastasis
or even a questionable
fracture on x-ray, an MRI
is a good follow-up test.
MRI is structural information.
An EMG is functional
information, information on
how the nerves are working.
It's not for pain. It can't
give you information on pain
fibers because the signal
coming from those small,
unmyelinated, excuse me, C
fibers gets buried in the
bigger signal from the more
robust, larger alpha fibers.
It's a very uncomfortable
test, so I don't order
unless there's a need. And
a need would be concrete
findings of numbness or
weakness on a physical exam.
This test can tell you
where the lesion is. If
somebody has neurological
lesions in their leg, I'm
sorry, neurological symptoms
in their leg, it doesn't
mean it's coming from
their nerve root. It could
also be coming from the
peripheral nerve in their leg
it could be coming from
the lumbar plexus this can
also tell you if it's a more
generalized polyneuropathy
from a systemic disease
and that might be the
case particularly if they
have symptoms in both
legs as opposed to a more
structural mononeuropathy
the only test that can
really prove if something is
painful or not is a nerve
block for spondylosis I would
do medial branch blocks
all the time, just a little
lidocaine over that nerve
that gives sensation to
the facet joint. If their pain
goes away for a few hours,
it means the pain was
coming from that structure.
Epidurals are rarely done
purely as diagnostic. Sometimes
a surgeon will request it
to prove that it's a pain
generator before they
operate, but it's not common.
Most people inject steroids,
which makes it more of a
treatment and less diagnostically
specific okay so back
to some pathology before
going on i just want to
mention that i know there's
a lot of information in these
slides and i'm not touching
on everything necessarily
it's an important topic
because it's so common so
i wanted to put more
information rather than less
but i don't want to make it
an excessively long lecture
so i'm going to speak on
the things that i feel
are important for you to
know now but i left the extra
stuff in there for your
reference and if you're
especially interested in it
a quick google search will
usually elucidate some
things that might be a little
unclear and if it doesn't
feel free to email me or
reach out to me find me in
lab or whatever and we can
discuss it at length that's
fine okay so the sacrum is
sort of controversial most
people do agree that it
can be a source of pain but
you should be aware that
some don't think so and in
fact they don't think that
there's any movement there
at all that's misguided
Why have an articulation
there at all then?
There is movement
in the SI joint. The
question is why?
What's the purpose?
So when you walk, one leg
shoots forward, making
that enominate want
to rotate posteriorly.
And the other leg trails,
and it's pinned down
on the ground by your
weight. So that enominate
on the other side wants
to rotate anteriorly.
So it's like you have
this bony ring, and you're
grabbing it from either
end, and you're twisting
it in opposite directions
like a figure eight.
Something has to
absorb those forces.
That's the predominant
role of the SI joint.
So it's sort of kidney
-shaped. It's not really
sagittally oriented.
This is a lateral view.
It's actually kind of
oblique. Some people confuse
one of these joint lines
for a fracture on x-ray.
But it's not. It's
just the joint line.
This is what a
fracture looks like.
On the right, you
have an MRI with some
surrounding bony edema,
which is the white.
These sacral insufficiency
fractures happen in the
elderly a lot. Elderly
people often have fusion
of joints as things get
kind of calcified over the
years. They also often
have osteoporosis. A fused
SI joint and weaker bone
illustrates something
very interesting. The
fracture usually runs parallel
to the SI joints. It's
as if all those forces in
walking are taking the
path of least resistance,
and if they can't get
absorbed by the SI joint
because it's fused or
ankylosed now, they recreate
it with the weaker bone
right along the same path.
So these are the age ranges.
The reason it happens
in pregnancy is because
there's this hormone named
relaxin that kind of
surges through the body to
make for a more accommodating
birth canal and it
loosens the ligaments that
compromises the si joint
stability it's holding up
about 70 of your weight
with your arms head and
leg i'm sorry and trunk
if this is in a younger
person particularly
male in their 20s i'm going
to be thinking something
more like ankylosing
spondylitis and so
you check x-rays and you
get blood work as well
Overall for SI joint
dysfunction the presentation
is very similar to
radiculopathy so you're going
to go through the same
history and physical exam.
The physical exam can be a
little bit trickier though.
Almost all of these
tests don't mean
a whole lot by
themselves. In general
groups of tests
are more reliable.
Different studies have
looked at different clusters
for specificity and sensitivity.
In general I just do
a bunch of them and depending
on how many start coming
back as positive, it
starts to form my diagnosis
and I'll start looking to
rule it in or out. Trigger
points.
So I've done entire lectures
on trigger points, so
I'm going to give you a
very brief version of it. So
when you contract, say,
your biceps muscle, you can
palpate this really hard
globe-like formation on your
arm. Well, if just a couple
of muscle fibers contract,
they'll form a similar
rounded structure, but it'll
feel like a little pee in
a background of otherwise
relaxed muscles. And if you
palpate proximal and distal
to that P, you'll feel
these taut bands of fibers
that are being pulled on.
The contraction itself is
not voluntary. There are
various conditions, mechanical
conditions that give rise
to these. And when you
press on it, it has pain over
that P, and then it refers
in a very specific pattern
that's different for
each muscle, and it's been
mapped out for each muscle.
Enough for you to know
now that it can contribute
to lower back pain,
and it can be a cause.
With the quadratus
lumborum, if you have
back pain over here,
it will typically
give you a referral
to the buttock.
For iliopsoas, it'll
look more like an
L2 or L3 radiculopathy,
where it radiates
just to that proximal
anterior thigh.
And then for piriformis,
it can look like an L5
or an S1, where it starts
to go down the back
of the thigh. And sometimes
a true radiculopathy
won't pass the knee. It
often does, but sometimes
it just sort of stays
put there depending
on how bad that nerve
root is being compressed.
So when people talk about
piriformis syndrome, they
always get into these
different permutations of
how the sciatic nerve is
related to the piriformis
muscle. It either pierces
through it or bifurcates
or it runs underneath it
and the piriformis can
kind of press on it. I'm
not going to get into
any of that. You can look
it up. It's never made
any difference to me
clinically whatsoever. other.
And you don't typically
have actual back pain with
this syndrome. It's usually
pain deep in the buttock and
down the posterior thigh
to the back of the knee.
Now, even in legit radiculopathy,
numbness is a sketchy
finding. People always say
they have numbness, even
when the EMG shows normal,
perfectly functioning sensory
nerves. It's probably
paresthesia, which is not
numbness, and it can make
things confusing for patients.
When there's real numbness,
it's a solid finding
and you find that the
patients are very,
very definite and specific
about it. This almost
never happens with
piriformis syndrome and
motor and reflex changes
are even less likely.
The gait might be ontalgic,
which is to say that
it's a painful gait.
Otherwise, the gait is normal.
Actively contracting
the muscle causes it to
bulge, like I mentioned
with the biceps, and
that can put pressure
on the sciatic nerve.
Stretching it with internal
rotation of the hip makes
the muscle taut, and that
can also put pressure on
the sciatic nerve. And
so either of these can be
provocative maneuvers. When a
patient is laying their supine
with piriformis syndrome,
you'll often find that
their leg is resting in
external rotation. That's not
an active external rotation.
So it actually slackens
the muscle and takes pressure
off the sciatic nerve.
So the psoas is not just a
hip flexor. It has a very
active role as stabilizing
and moving the lumbar
spine that psoas syndrome
is kind of a spectrum thing
there's this image confirmable
psoas tendonitis or
bursitis and that usually
comes with athletes that
do a lot of hip flexion
or plyometrics and then
there's this softer diagnosis
where it's just a really
tight psoas that maybe
has a trigger point in it
because it attaches to the
lumbar spine that can cause
back pain. Because it
inserts on the lesser
trochanter, it can also cause
groin pain and thigh pain.
These are the main
symptoms, and they look sort
of like an L2 or an L3
disc pathology. Now, some
sources say it can also
give posterior thigh pain
in the contralateral
limb. I don't think this
happens very often, and
the mechanics are a little
convoluted, so I only tell
you this in case it comes
up on someone else's
exam, you've heard of it.
the physical exam is as
you would expect it with
difficulty getting the hip to
neutral now this can manifest
as excessive lordosis with
anterior pelvic tilting
or just standing there bent
over and if it's just one
psoas that it's affected because
it's pulling unilaterally
it can give you a type
one lumbar curve with
convexity on the side of
the tight psoas and with the
pelvis sort of shifting away
to kind of even itself out.
You may even find sacrosomatic
dysfunctions that
are related to it.
But the big thing
is the Thomas test.
So can you spot what's
wrong with this picture?
It's that lower leg
past the knee on the
positive version. It isn't
hanging straight down.
So the psoas doesn't cross
the knee. It should have no
effect on the knee at all.
but the rectus femoris
crosses both the hip and the
knee, so if it's tight, you
may get the knee unable to
relax and settle at 90 degrees.
But for psoas tightness,
it's just the thigh that
doesn't come to rest on the
table, and that lower leg
should be vertical. So this
is technically wrong, but
I thought it was illustrative,
so I included this one.
As often as not, the
source of low back
pain isn't able to be
clearly identified.
Nobody really knows if
modic changes that I talked
about before actually
cause pain. This is sort
of new territory. They're
starting to think that
it does, but for a long
time they weren't sure.
Facet joints definitely
can, but a lot of times
it's a mix of spine,
muscle, and even connective
tissue, which is why
back pain can be so
difficult to treat sometimes.
And we certainly don't
have any treatments for
any kind of ligament
or connective tissue
pain generators,
so it can be a
pretty mixed bag.
These are all things
that may appear in
your back pain patient
that may be contributing
to their pain or
may be coincidental.
They only matter in
context. If one or two of
these fits into the story,
the mechanical story
that you're building your
diagnosis on, then you
have more confidence in
it. It's kind of like
somatic dysfunctions. A
lot of you have them in
lab, but you don't
necessarily have symptoms.
Okay, so I have a bunch
of cases over here.
I'm not going to go through
them. I really included
them in here just sort of
for you to go through. You
can read the history and
then I have a differential
diagnosis for you. Then I
have the physical exam and
then I've kind of worked
through the differential
diagnosis. I've crossed things
off my list. I've circled
my most likely and then
I've given you my diagnostic
plan. This is really just
to kind of finesse your
understanding of the lecture
material. But if you do
have any questions on
these, again, feel free to
email me or find me in lab
and we can talk about them.
Again, you don't want
to sit on weakness,
especially if the
weakness is getting
rapidly progressive,
because then it can be
permanent if it's not
surgically corrected.
And again, caudate
quina syndrome is
the last thing that
you want to miss.
Metastasis often goes to the
spine. It has a different
feel to it, though. They
don't talk about this makes
it hurt more, that makes
it feel better. It's really
like this creepy, deep pain
at night in bed, and it
doesn't change no matter
what position they get into.
You ask about constitutional
symptoms, of course,
and then an x-ray or an
MR can show you stuff.
If you get the MR to
evaluate the soft tissue,
you get it with contrast
to roulette metastases.
If you have reason to
believe that there's an
infection, either of the
disc or osteomyelitis, that's
also an indication for
a contrast-enhanced MRI.
Here's a picture of the
cauda in case you forgot it.
things that can choke
off the central canal
I've color-coded it
for your convenience
two things I want to
mention that may not be as
obvious hematoma you think
of this if they're on
blood thinners and there
was some incident like a
trauma or if they had a
recent procedure like an
epidural where the where
a needle was going off
into that space if there's
a compression fracture
in osteoporosis sometimes
some of those fragments
of the vertebral body
can retro pulse into the
canal. So these are just
all things to be aware of.
All kinds of things can
refer pain to the back. I'm
not going to test you on
any of this. It's not really
something to memorize
either, just something that
you should understand. If
you understand the why of
these things and why they
would cause back pain,
it'll surface from your
subconscious when you need it.
Okay,
email me, find me in lab
or we can meet and chat
if you have questions
and I hope you had fun.